<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-05-20T15:50:20-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ken Norris</title><subtitle>Welcome to my ad-hoc collection of thoughts on energy and enviromental policy, photos of paintings, and possibly bike tour miscellanea in the future.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Electricity systems and interconnections</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/energy-env/2021/05/19/interconnections.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Electricity systems and interconnections" /><published>2021-05-19T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-05-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/energy-env/2021/05/19/interconnections</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/energy-env/2021/05/19/interconnections.html">&lt;p&gt;Canada has vast resources of hydroelectric generating capacity. In British Columbia up to 97% of electricity in a given year is generated from massive hydroelectric dams, while in Quebec this percentage is roughly 95%. While BC has huge hydro resources, a small amount of that electricity goes across the provincial border to Alberta. Alberta has historically depended on coal to generate electricity. As one of the most potent sources of greenhouse gases on our planet, the sooner all coal fired power plants are closed, the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canada now has a country-wide carbon tax. Before the carbon tax one could imagine there being some preference among Albertans for lower cost local electricity but now with coal fired plants facing additional production costs (beyond the increasing cost of their input product) due to the carbon tax, why don’t BC and Alberta engage in inter-provincial trade to take advantage of clean (and cheaper) resources? To answer this question&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each province independently operates and monitors their own grid. This has created a patchwork of different regulatory environments spanning from competitive markets to provincial monopoly utilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All net-zero scenarios are capital intensive. Before considering the substantial mobilization of risk capital for development and construction, institutional realities need to be explored to fully understand how best to target these massive long-term investments. As the price of emitting one ton of carbon increases, pressure on large industrial polluters to decarbonize increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am going to propose that a substantial opportunity exists for increasing capacity across the system by interconnecting existing networks. By integrating grid resources between neighbouring provinces, Canada can more quickly move along the path to retire coal-fired power plants and decarbonize the grid. While Canada derives a large proportion of its electricity from hydroelectric and nuclear sources, the increase in demand created increased electrification of both industry and transport will require additional capacity from generators to power the additional baseline load.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across Canadian provinces, there are substantial differences in emissions profiles. Historically, Alberta and Ontario have been the highest emitting provinces. However, since 2005, emission patterns in these two provinces have diverged. Emissions in Alberta have increased by 40 Mt (17%) since 2005, primarily as a result of the expansion of oil and gas operations. In contrast, Ontario’s emissions have decreased by 42 Mt (21%) since 2005, owing primarily to the closure of coal-fired electricity generation plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discussion of whether or not additional new oil and gas operations is compatible with emissions reductions will have to wait for another post. I’m going to focus here on an opportunity to decarbonize the electricity sector by interconnecting the electricity grids of adjacent Canadian provinces. Currently, many more North-South connections between provinces and US states exists than do connections East-West in Canada. This means that while Manitoba generates nearly one hundred percent of electricity from hydroelectric sources, Saskatchewan generates a neglible amount from non-fossil fuel sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electricity usage in all forecasted models of a net zero scenario is projected to increase. As electrification of vehicles and space and water heating increases, as will  electricity demand which will require upgrades to electricity distribution networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typical electricity usage over a 24-hour period follows a wave function, with the peak being around dinner time when people are home cooking dinner and turning lights and TVs on. The overall usage in the system then declines overnight to pick back up in the morning. To help smooth out demand when more facets of our life are electrified there are clever automation strategies that can be built into systems for EV charging or heat pump systems to, for example, take advantage of lower overnight electricity demand periods. These can help lower the stress on distribution networks, and consequently overall cost of upgrading the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, given the huge increase needed in electrification, this won’t be sufficient to meet the new demands on the system.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[&quot;Ken Norris&quot;]</name></author><category term="energy-env" /><summary type="html">Canada has vast resources of hydroelectric generating capacity. In British Columbia up to 97% of electricity in a given year is generated from massive hydroelectric dams, while in Quebec this percentage is roughly 95%. While BC has huge hydro resources, a small amount of that electricity goes across the provincial border to Alberta. Alberta has historically depended on coal to generate electricity. As one of the most potent sources of greenhouse gases on our planet, the sooner all coal fired power plants are closed, the better.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Canadian carbon tax</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/energy-env/2021/05/02/carbon-tax-intro.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Canadian carbon tax" /><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-05-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/energy-env/2021/05/02/carbon-tax-intro</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/energy-env/2021/05/02/carbon-tax-intro.html">&lt;p&gt;In 2018, as part of its commitment to reduce emissions in the fight against climate change, Canada passed the Greenhouse Gas Pollution Pricing Act (GGPPA) which placed a charge on each tonne of carbon dioxide (CO2) emitted by polluters. Currently the charge, or tax, is set at $30 per tonne and set to rise each year by $15 to $170 per tonne by 2030. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pollution has a cost. As evidence mounts that GHGs cause and contribute to poor health outcomes for individuals and the planet, a carbon tax quantifies this cost and acts as a mechanism to drive pollution reductions. By putting a price on carbon emissions, governments encourage  individuals and businesses to account for the amount of pollution in their consumptive and productive decisions to then adjust towards lower carbon intensive alternatives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, the GGPPA is a revenue neutral taxation program. This means that the government does not collect the proceeds to fund its own activities, instead the money is returned to Canadians through the tax system. The system is set up to take into account the average energy usage of a household by province, so in Saskatchewan where people drive far distances and have higher heating costs in the winter, the amount a family can expect to receive is higher than in Ontario. The benchmark for rebates has been set up such that the average middle class family in each province will receive money on net (rebate minus tax) rather than pay for the carbon tax. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point it’s reasonable to ask, ‘If I’m just going to receive the money back as a cheque, how is this impacting what I consume?’ A brief example to illustrate: suppose when you buy beer you usually purchase PBR or Miller High Life. If the price of PBR doubles while High Life stays the same, you will buy more High Life, regardless of whether or not your income has changed. The tax mechanism provides incentive to shift consumption over to the next best, and relatively cheaper, option, whether that be your individual decision to purchase an electric vehicle, or utility switching to wind powered generation rather than a coal-fired power plant for electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Policy-makers prefer the carbon tax as an instrument to regulate greenhouse gas emissions as the tax imposes a cost per tonne of carbon that allows the market to determine what alternatives are financially competitive, as opposed to a policy that picks a specific substitute to replace polluting technologies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The carbon tax, as it is specified, also provides a predictable schedule of future costs, increasing at a constant rate of $15 per tonne per year. From a planning perspective, for both government and industry, this is considered optimal, as the price per tonne of GHGs increases, there is definitely a return on costly investment that tackles the most pollution heavy of their activities first.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[&quot;Ken Norris&quot;]</name></author><category term="energy-env" /><summary type="html">In 2018, as part of its commitment to reduce emissions in the fight against climate change, Canada passed the Greenhouse Gas Pollution Pricing Act (GGPPA) which placed a charge on each tonne of carbon dioxide (CO2) emitted by polluters. Currently the charge, or tax, is set at $30 per tonne and set to rise each year by $15 to $170 per tonne by 2030. </summary></entry></feed>